Guide to the Foster Hall Collection, 1800-1952 CAM.FHC.2011.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Foster Family, 1800-1952; II.
  - Foster Family Manuscripts, 1800-1900; 3.
    - Correspondence, 1800-1950
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., March 24, 1840; C689
        Travel plans; congressional improvements bill; we think it's time to receive another letter from Stephen, I hope he is attentive to his studies…tell him his old Uncle Struthers looks to him to become a very great man, he says he is confident he possess.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., April 27, 1840; C690
        Scolded Stephen for not writing & then received a letter from him dated some time past; congressional news; family news.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., May 31, 1840; C691
        Explaining his reasons for coming to Pittsburgh: land matter & debt; business matters; stock certificate enclosed.
      - From Eliza C. Foster to William Foster, Jr., August 7, 1840; C692
        Thanking him for letter & $20; As to Stephen I leave everything re his future to your judgment West Point or the navy I have no choice; you are not only his brother but his father; family & social news; My fears in relation to [pa] have ended.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., September 27, 1840; C693
        En route to Philadelphia to pursue claim; apprising William of where he and Eliza will be.
      - From Eliza C. Foster to Morrison Foster, October 7, 1840; C694
        At Ann Eliza's house; urging him to take care of his health; family news.
      - From William B. Foster, George Poe, and James Dunlop to William B. Foster, Jr., November 7, 1840; C695
        Statements for his claim against George Poe, Jr.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., November 16, 1840; C696
        Just received letter & wanted to acknowledge it; congressional news; family news; news of the McKelvy unpaid note.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., December 1, 1840; C697
        Enclosing articles abusing the Gov.; text for resolution to protect Gov.'s name; encouraging him to invest in land; family news.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., February 13, 1841; C698
        George Poe suit; info regarding small steam engine; legislation on state improvements.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., February 17, 1841; C699
        Thanking him for $10; money Thomas Wick owes Wm. Jr., Thomas Wick's illness; pleased to hear of his impending marriage.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., February 22, 1841; C700
        Enclosed copy of his claim against Poe; Thomas Wick still ill but will most definitely repay money owed.
      - From Eliza C. Foster to William Foster, Jr., February 24, 1841; C701
        Torn in half; William's impending marriage; family news.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., February 27, 1841; C702
        The money Thomas Wick owes him and William, Sr's, plan to get it.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., March 30, 1841; C703
        Forwarded his letter to Thomas Wick; William, Sr's, claim; state appropriate; his lack of employment; Bank Bill; financial state.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., April 22, 1841; C704
        His claim against Poe; his plans for Henry; travel plans; family news.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., April 28, 1841; C705
        Account of local fire; encouraging William to contact Mr. Stevens about getting insurance on his houses; newspaper account of St. Louis murder.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., May 15, 1841; C706
        His travel and work plans; Thomas Wick is on the mend; family news.
      - From William B. Foster to William Foster, Jr., June 11, 1841; C707
        Returned from trip to Kentucky; news of Thomas and Henrietta Wick; will be going to Butler to settle land claims; travel plans; family news; drought.
      - From Eliza C. Foster to William Foster, Jr., August 14, 1841; C708
        Need to make new living arrangements b/c of cost; wants to hear the current info on his engagement but has told no one; Stephen refuses to stay at Canonsburg & wants to come home; family news; wishing him well.
      - From F.M. Hutchinson to ?, July 14, 1858; C721
      - From the Grand Lodge of PA to Alfred Morneweck, February 21, 1931; C729
      - From Thomas Burnside to William Foster, Jr., June 19, 1835; C736
        Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From William B. Foster, Jr., to William H. Packer, Esq., June 17, 1839; C737
        William Foster, Jr.'s, job application to the Engineering Dept. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From James Buchanan to James Clarke, esq., January 31, 1839; C738
        Letter of recommendation for William B. Foster for engineer position with Canal Commission. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - Declaration of the Office of the Pennsylvania and Ohio Canal Company to accept the resignation of William Foster, Jr., April 13, 1837; C640
      - Letter of reference for William Foster, Jr., from board of Green River Comms., June 19, 1935; C635
      - From H. Gold Rogers to William F. Packer, March 3, 1839; C739
      - From Chester Butler to the PA Canal Commission, Dec. 29, 1841; C740
      - From Senator and representatives of PA to David R. Porter, Governor, January 1842; C741
      - From John H. Dincork to PA Canal Commission, C742
      - From J.B. Guchiev to PA Canal Commission, Jan. 22, 1842; C743
      - From Thomas Philips to the PA Canal Commission, January 24, 1842; C744
      - From David Lynch to the PA Canal Commission, January 25, 1842; C745
      - From William Packer to the PA Canal Commission, January 31, 1842; C746
      - From William B. Foster, Jr., to the PA Canal Commission, February 3, 1842; C747
        Cover letter stating his desire to apply as Principal Engineer. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From Salisbury to PA Canal Commission, February 5, 1842; C748
      - From George Crawford to PA Canal Commission, 1842; C749
      - From Henry Petteboue to the PA Canal Commission, October 6, 1842; C750
      - From Henry Web to PA Canal Commission, October 10, 1842; C751
      - From Senator J. Horton to PA Canal Commission, October 15, 1842; C752
      - From C.S. Ward to PA Canal Commission, October 18, 1842; C753
      - From William B. Foster, Jr., to PA Canal Commission, October 24, 1842; C754
      - From George Crawford to Pa Canal Commission, January 16, 1843; C755
      - From Jacob Hill to PA Canal Commission, February 1, 1843; C756
      - From G.G. Palmer to William B. Foster, Jr., January 8, 1840; C757
        Barlow & Evans tract of land. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From E.W. Stephen to William B. Foster, Jr., July 21, 1840; C758
        Proposed building, other financial matters. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From E.W. Stephen to William B. Foster, Jr., January 30, 1841; C759
        Bills for work on William's houses, information on money that William owes him. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From William Hull to William B. Foster, Jr., January 26, 1842; C760
        Letter stating William paid him and that his suit against William has been dismissed. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From Stetly? to William B. Foster, Jr., February 10, 1846; C761
        Bill for boarding the family. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From John White to Henry Parrish, Esq., January 25, 1847; C762
        Letter of introduction for William, Jr. & Others discussing constructing new canal. Business Correspondence of William Foster, Jr.
      - From J.W. Weidermeyer to Morrison Foster, October 27, 1887; C763a.
      - From J.W. Weidermeyer to Morrison Foster, March 23, 1887; C763b.
      - From J.W. Weidermeyer to Morrison Foster, March 23, 1887; C763c.
      - From J.W. Weidermeyer to Morrison Foster, October 24, 1887; C763d.
      - From J.W. Weidermeyer to Morrison Foster, March 19, 1886; C763e.
      - From J.W. Weidermeyer to Morrison Foster, March 22, 1887; C763f.
      - From Jessie Welsh Rose to Morrison Foster, 1900; C765
        Includes newspaper clipping about Foster monument.
      - Postcard to Morrison Foster from T.J. Keenan, September 6, 1900; C768a.
      - Freight receipt, December 7, 1896; C768b.
      - To Morrison Foster from Charles H. Niehaus, December 5, 1896; C768c.
      - From Morrison Foster to T.J. Keenan, Jr., September 6, 1900; C768d.
      - To Morrison Foster from T.J. Keenan, Jr., March 26, 1893; C768e.
      - To Morrison Foster from Charles H. Niehaus, March 27, 1897; C768f.
      - Agreement between Hudson Foster and William Foster, March 24, 1831; C775a.
      - Agreement between Hudson Foster and William Foster and Edward C. Biddle, October 29, 1835; C775b.
      - Power of Attorney for William Foster, November 29, 1832; C775c.
      - Power of Attorney for Hudson Foster, October 29, 1835; C775d.
      - Power of Attorney for John Land, June 16, 1836; C775e.
      - Power of Attorney for John Land, September 3, 1832; C775f.
      - Power of Attorney for Hudson Foster, October 29, 1835; C775g.
      - Power of Attorney for Hudson Foster, March 29, 1831; C775h.
      - Power of Attorney for William Foster, November 29, 1832; C775i.
      - To Henrietta Wick from Eliza C. Foster, February 14, 1841; C776
        Brother William's job hunt; visit to President and Governor with William and Henry?; current home.
      - From Jesse A. Baker to Morrison Foster, January 26, 1871; C846
        Regarding Baker's play "An Evening with Foster."
      - From Hubert P. Main to Morrison Foster, January 10, 1870; C847
        Requesting Stephen's autograph for his collection.
      - From William Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, February 11, 1864; C848
        Have collected all of Stephen's songs as he requested and will forward them to him as soon as copies are available.
      - From C.E. Leslie, Chicago Music Co., to Morrison Foster, October 27, 1887; C849
        Asking permission to use "My Old Kentucky Home" for the Freedman Choral Union.
      - From WL Luisley of the Lyons Weekly Republican to Morrison Foster, February 26, 1864; C850
        Asking for a list of Stephen's compositions and for information on what publisher publishes Stephen's hymns.
      - From L.M. Van Bukkelen to Morrison Foster, March 29, 1888; C851
        Incorrectly addressed to "Harrison" Foster; asking permission to publish "Old Dog Tray" as part of the Kappa Alpha Fraternity's society song book.
      - From Oliver Ditson & Co. to Morrison Foster, May 5, 1888; C852
        They have no objection to Morrison publishing a collection of Foster's songs, lyrics only, as long as Marion & Jane don't, but he cannot publish the music.
      - From J. Howard Wert to Morrison Foster, August 8, 1888; C853
        Asking permission to use "My Old Kentucky Home" and potentially other songs for publication in a leaflet.
      - From John D. Champlain, Jr., Charles Scribner & Sons, to Morrison Foster, January 11, 1888; C854
        Asking for biographical info on Foster, including list of works & picture if possible.
      - From Edward Brinley to Publishers of the Pittsburg Chronicle, January 30, 1864; C855a.
        Requesting a copy of an article on Stephen Foster and any photos they may have.
      - From A. Kleber to Morrison Foster, February 9, 1864; C855b.
        Cover letter for other letters included in 855.
      - From Edward Brinley to H. Kleber & Co., February 1, 1864; C855c.
        Asking for a complete list of Foster's songs & proposing that they put out a collection of the songs, lots of praise of Foster as a composer.
      - From Edward Brinley to Morrison Foster, February 15, 1864; C855d.
        Suggesting the complete works collection.
      - From W.F. Williams to Charles McKnight, January 26, 1864; C856a.
        Enclosing a copy of the NY Evening Post's Tribute to Foster. Reminiscing about how popular Foster was internationally. Requesting a memento of Foster. Includes postscript that Harpers wants him to write an article on Foster.
      - From Charles McKnight to Morrison Foster, January 30, 1864; C856b.
        Forwarding W.F. Williams' letter to him.
      - From George P. Miller to Morrison Foster, June 22, 1897; C857a.
        Sending news clipping he thought Morrison might be interested in.
      - From George Miller to Morrison Foster, July 21, 1897; C857b.
        Providing him with correspondent's name.
      - From Jason C. Stevenson to Morrison Foster, November 21, 1898; C858
        Remarking on Morrison's biography project; giving information on the Stevenson family.
      - From Ticknor & Co. to Morrison Foster, May 3, 1887; C859a.
        Wants to create illustrated editions of "Old Folks at Home" and "My Old Kentucky Home" (Copeland editions). Morrison's response on back indicates they may proceed provided he makes arrangements with Pond and Ditson and that compensation go to his brother's heirs.
      - From Ticknor & Co. to Morrison Foster, May 14, 1887; C859b.
        Thanks him for his letter, will proceed as he advised.
      - From Ticknor & Co., to Morrison Foster, June 10, 1887; C859c.
        Letting him know they have made arrangements with Pond & Ditson and describing the volume. Asking for images to use.
      - From Ticknor & Co. to Morrison Foster, October 7, 1887; C859d.
        They've decided to omit the biography from the book. Giving him publishing information.
      - From Oliver Ditson & Co. to Morrison Foster, November 23, 1887; C859e.
        Enclosing a copy of the illustrated edition of "Old Folks."
      - From Oliver Ditson to Morrison Foster, December 5, 1887; C859f.
        Asking if he received the illustrated "old folks" and enclosing other complimentary copies of sheet music.
      - From Ticknor & Co. to Morrison Foster, October 29, 1887; C859g.
        Have mailed copies of melodies to Mrs. Buchanan per Morrison's request. Quoting cost of duplicating portrait.
      - From Charles Neure of the Athens Academy to Morrison Foster, June 2, 1897; C860
        Asking for a copy of "Tioga Waltz" to put in cornerstone of new Library.
      - From John H. McCrury to Morrison Foster, August 10, 1892; C861a.
        Requesting information on Foster to include in Pittsburgh & Western PA Historical biographical sketches.
      - From J.W. McCrury to Morrison Foster, August 17, 1892; C861b.
        Asking to receive materials by Dec. 1. Morrison's response on page indicates he mailed the requested items.
      - From G.A. Townsend to Morrison Foster, July 16, 1893; C862a.
        Thanking him for his letter and discussing Stephen's biography.
      - From G.A. Townsend to Morrison Foster, January 2, 1894; C862b.
        Suggesting possible publishers.
      - Card from G.A. Townsend to Morrison Foster, undated; C862c.
        Sorry he wasn't able to meet with him when he was in town.
      - Article/advertisement "Gapland Mountain Cottages", undated; C862d.
      - From William V. Alexander to Morrison Foster, May 1, 1900; C863a.
        Asking for a photo of Foster's grave for use in the Ladies Home Journal.
      - From William Alexander to Morrison Foster, May 4, 1900; C863b.
        Thanking him for referring him to Percy Smith.
      - From William Alexander to Morrison Foster, May 14, 1900; C863c.
        Percy Smith has no photo of the grave but believe Morrison does. Morrison responds on bottom of the letter that he sent Alexander a copy of Biography, Songs &c including the photo.
      - From Edward S. Ellis to Morrison Foster, June 23, 1900; C864a.
        Pond has promised him a Foster manuscript to present to Judge Reed. Wants to know if Morrison has two copies of bio sketch he could give him. Morrison's response on bottom of letter indicates that he should send $4 to Percy Smith to obtain copies.
      - From Edward Ellis to Morrison Foster, July 7, 1900; C864b.
        Would like to write a tribute to Foster. Asking Morrison to clarify a few facts.
      - From W.H. Griffiths to Morrison Foster, March 31, 1892; C865
        Asking for a souvenir of Foster.
      - From John Scott to Morrison Foster, July 31, 1896; C866
        Received biography; Foster genealogy--John is a descendant of Violet Foster & Josiah Scott and has prepared the book Hugh Scott and his descendants.
      - From J.B. Wambaugh to Morrison Foster, April 21, 1897; C867
        Requesting some of Foster's plantation melodies.
      - From C.W. Des Islets to Morrison Foster, April 1, 1892; C868a.
        Asking for a chance to call him to get information on Stephen for a Foster program Jefferson Academy will be doing.
      - From C.W. Des Islets to Morrison Foster, May 2, 1892; C868b.
        Thanking him for loaning her papers which she returned with this letter, allowing her to call on him, etc.
      - Correspondence between Morrison Foster and and Monroe Crannell, regarding "Old Folks at Home", 1889; C869
        - From Monroe Crannell to Postmaster at Pittsburgh, February 28, 1889; C869a
        - From Monroe Crannell to Morrison Foster, March 16, 1889; C869b
        - From Monroe Crannell to Morrison Foster, March 11, 1889; C869c
        - From Stephen C. Foster to E.P. Christy, May 25, 1852; C869d
          Included as enclosure for C869c correspondence from Monroe Crannell to Morrison Foster. Although Elliker states that the original of the 1852 letter is in the Foster collection, it apppears only this copy, made in Mr. Crannell's hand, is held by the Center for American Music. The whereabouts of the original document are not currently known.
          Pittsburgh, May 25, 1852
          E.P. Christy, Esq.
          As I once intimated to you, I had the intention of omitting my name on my Ethiopian songs, owing to the prejudice against them by some, which might injure my reputation as a writer of another style of music, but I find that by my efforts I have done a great deal to build up a taste for the Ethiopian songs among refined people by making the words suitable to their taste, instead of the trashy and really offensive words which belong to some of that order. Therefore I have concluded to reinstate my name on my songs and to pursue the Ethiopian business without fear or shame and lend all my energies to making the business live, at the same time that I will wish to establish my name as the best Ethiopian song-writer. But I am not encouraged in undertaking this so long as "The Old Folks At Home" stares me in the face with another's name on it. As it was at my own solicitation that you allowed your name to be placed on the song, I hope that the above reasons will be sufficient explanation for my desire to place my own name on it as author and composer, while at the same time I wish to leave the name of your band on the title page. This is a little matter of pride in myself which it will certainly be to your interest to encourage. On the receipt of your free consent to this proposition, I will, if you wish, willingly refund you the money which you paid me on that song, though it may have been sent me for other considerations than the one in question, and I promise in addition to write you an opening chorus in my best style, free of charge, and in any other way in my power to advance your interest hereafter. I find I cannot write at all unless I write for public approbation and get credit for what I write. As we may probably have a good deal of business with each other in our lives, it is best to proceed on a sure basis of confidence and good understanding, therefore I hope you will appreciate an author's feelings in the case and deal with me with your usual fairness. Please answer immediately.
          Very respectfully yours, Stephen C. Foster
          On the back of the letter it says
          S.C. Foster - A mean & contemptible - vascillating skunk & plagiarist - Pittsburg Pa May 1852 "Old Folks"
          then Crannell has added "copy of Christy's endorsement"
        - From Morrison Foster to Monroe Crannell, march 13, 1889; C869d
          copy of letter in Morrison's hand, written on the last page of C869c.
      - From Jos (?) C. Brummer to Jos. Eishbaum & Co., April 22, 1890; C872
        Requesting info on biography of Stephen Foster listed in Brainards Musical World.
      - From D.H. James to Jane Foster, October 14, 1885; C873
        Second Presbyterian church would like to give a Foster program and needs her help with a list of the songs.
      - From Marcus M. Henry to Morrison Foster, February 6, 1883; C874
        Requesting information on Foster for inclusion in a compilation of info on American popular composers.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, July 17, 1929; C875a.
        Seeking images to be included in Musical Courier "Pictorial Bibliography" article.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, July 31, 1929; C875b.
        Clarifying that a photographer could be sent to her home so that the items needn't leave her possession.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, August 8, 1929; C875c.
        Sorry that their letters crossed in the mail. Would appreciate her reading the article before it goes to print.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, August 16, 1929; C875d.
        Confirming time of photographer, asking after additional photos.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, undated; C875e.
        Thanking her for suggestions of additional photos and for sending a photo of Morrison to him.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, August 21, 1929; C875f.
        Arrangements with photographer, list of what he would like shot, and a wish list of other items he is seeking.
      - List of images sent by Mrs. Morneweck, August 24, 1929; C875g.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, August 28, 1929; C875h.
        Thanking her for pictures she sent. Thanking her for cooperating with the photographer.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, September 7, 1929; C875i.
        Thanking her for info on White Cottage and informing her of images they received from Federal Hill and the Cincinnati Public Library.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, December 28, 1929; C875j.
        Sending her the article to fact check.
      - From Evelyn Foster Morneweck to Grover Sims, January 1, 1930; C875k.
        The only thing she asks that he change in the Musical Courier article is the description of Stephen's grave being unkempt.
      - From Grover Sims to Evelyn Foster Morneweck, January 23, 1930; C875l.
        The change she suggested was made. The article should appear in January, at which point he'll forward a copy.
      - Pamphlet of Offerings from the Sims Visual Music Co., undated; C875m.
      - From E.H. Strickland to Oliver Ditson, February 13, 1882; C876a.
        Would like a sample of Foster's handwriting to put in a bound volume of his music that he's assembled for his private use. Note at bottom of letter (presumably to Morrison) asking if he can oblige this man's request.
      - From E.F. Strickland to Morrison Foster, March 14, 1882; C876b.
        Thanking him for his response to his request, though regrets that he wasn't able to send him his brother's handwriting. Enclosed a poem he wrote.
      - From E.H. Johnston to Henry Kleber, December 10, 1877; C877a.
        Asking him for a photo of Stephen Foster for his album of "American Notabilities."
      - From E.H. Johnson to Morrison Foster, March 13, 1878; C877b.